Guide to the Myra A. Keen Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Myra A. Keen papers
1936-1981
SC0305
Keen, A. Myra (Angeline Myra), 1905-1986
1.5 Linear feet
Papers consist of correspondence with colleagues and former students, 1936-65; correspondence with her publisher Stanford University Press, 1937-80; and papers (correspondence, memos, reports, minutes, and financial records) relating to the Department of Earth Sciences and fossil and shell collections, 1937-1981. Correspondents include Edwin C. Allison, Ralph Arnold, Agustin Ayala-Castanares, Reginald Wright Barker, Herdis Bentson, Eliot Blackwelder, Welsey Roswell Coe, J. Wyatt Durham, Richard H. Jahns, Konrad Krauskopf, Owen T. Marsh, Erwin Remson, Donald B. Tresidder, Charles E. Weaver, and Ray Lyman Wilbur.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Myra grew up on a cattle ranch in Colorado, about twenty miles south of Colorado Springs. Her parents farmed and raised cattle on the ranch. Myra rode a burro when she was four and bought her own horse when she was thirteen. She attended a one room school house for eight grades. She completed the eight grades in five years. Because of age qualifications she had to wait three years to attend high school.
She attended Colorado College and was elected to Phi Beta Kappa in 1929 and graduated in Psychology in 1930. She won a scholarship to Stanford where she earned a M.A. in Psychology and then earned her Ph. D. in Psychology from the University of California in 1934. When in Berkeley, Myra went into a small curio shop on University Avenue to buy a copy of National Geographic. She noticed some sea shells in a display case. The owner talked about the shells and Myra found herself going back again and again to look at them.
In 1934, in the middle of the Depression, Myra could not find any jobs in Psychology, plus she realized she was more interested in sea shells. During the summer she went to Monterey to learn about collecting sea shells. She spoke with Dr. Heath of the Hopkins Marine Station and was eventually introduced to Mrs. Ida Oldroyd, who as curator of shells at Stanford needed a helper. After a few month, encouraged by Professor Schenck, Myra began auditing some of his courses and became a Research Associate in Geology in 1936. In 1936 she became the Curator of Paleontology.
For one year during World War II, the Head of the Department, Dr. Blackwelder and Myra were the only instructional staff in the Department, though Myra was not on the teaching faculty.
In 1954, Myra was promoted to Assistant Professor of Paleontology in addition to her duties at Curator. In 1965 she was promoted to Professor. She became emeritus in 1970. While Myra was at Stanford she was one of ten professors, only three of whom were in the sciences.
After World War II, Dr. Hubert Schenck, a Stanford Geology professor working for General MacArthur in the re-building of Japan, had contact with the Emperor of Japan. The Emperor was a general biologist endmost interested in corals. He had a large collection. Dr. Schenck saw material in the collection that he felt was not properly identified. Dr. Schenck suggested that the material be sent of Dr. Keen to verified. That started a long correspondence ending in a private personal meeting between the Emperor and Dr. Keen in San Francisco in 1975.
Dr. Keen has written many journal articles and four books. Her Sea Shells of Tropical West America is a classic work. In addition, she has helped hundreds of people at other institutions in various ways, particularly in telling them the correct name of their shells.
After Dr. Keen retired in 1970, she remained active in the department.
Description of the Collection
Papers consist of correspondence with colleagues and former students, 1936-65; correspondence with her publisher Stanford University Press, 1937-80; and papers (correspondence, memos, reports, minutes, and financial records) relating to the Department of Earth Sciences and fossil and shell collections, 1937-1981. Correspondents include Edwin C. Allison, Ralph Arnold, Agustin Ayala-Castanares, Reginald Wright Barker, Herdis Bentson, Eliot Blackwelder, Welsey Roswell Coe, J. Wyatt Durham, Richard H. Jahns, Konrad Krauskopf, Owen T. Marsh, Erwin Remson, Donald B. Tresidder, Charles E. Weaver, and Ray Lyman Wilbur.
Access Terms
Allison, Edwin C.; Arnold, Ralph, 1875-1961; Ayala-Castanares, Agustin.; Barker, Reginald Wright.; Barthel, K. Werner.; Bentson, Herdis, 1914-; Blackwelder, Eliot, 1880; Coe, Wesley Roswell, 1869-1960.; Durham, J. Wyatt.; Jahns, Richard H. (Richard Henry), 1915-1983; Keen, A. Myra (Angeline Myra), 1905-1986; Krauskopf, Konrad Bates, 1910-; Marsh, Owen Thayer.; Remson, Irwin.; Stanford University. School of Earth Sciences; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand, 1894-1948; Weaver, Charles E. (Charles Edwin), 1880-; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Mollusks--North America.; Mollusks--Pacific Coast (America).; Paleontology
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Biographical sketches of Myra Keen (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stanford Natural History Museum 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stanford-Palo Alto Natural History Museum 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Paleontological Type Collection Fund 1946-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Conchological Collection 1943-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Paleontology Collections Committee 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invertebrate Fossil Collection Questionnaire 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department of Earth Sciences 1943-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Department of Earth Sciences 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanford University 1945-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stanford University 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anonymous Paleontology Fund Expenses (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Conchological Publication Fund Expenses (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Cenzoic Collection 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Cenzoic Collection 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Cenzoic Collection 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Cenzoic Collection 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Oldroyd Fund 1941-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Reviews of published works (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Stanford University Press Correspondence 1937-1980, folder 1 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Stanford University Press Correspondence 1937-1980, folder 2 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Stanford University Press Correspondence 1937-1980, folder 3 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stanford University Press, Contracts and Sales 1945-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Stanford University Press, Royalty statements 1952-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - H. Bruce Franklin (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “A”, folder 1 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “A”, folder 2 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “A”, folder 3 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “B”, folder 1 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “B”, folder 2 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “B”, folder 3 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “B”, folder 4 of 4 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “C”, folder 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “C”, folder 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “C”, folder 3 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “D”, folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “D”, folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “E-K”, folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “E-K”, folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “L-M”, folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “L-M”, folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “N-R”, folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “N-R”, folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “S-T” (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, author beginning with “U-W” (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Owen Marsh 1953-1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Ray Lyman Wilbur 1936-1943 (Box 3, Folder 15)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Allison, Edwin C. 2 10
Arnold, Ralph 2 11
Ayala-Castanares, Agustin 2 11
Barker, R. Wright, 2 12 Shell Oil Co.
Barthel, K. Werne 2 13 State Museum of Geology, Munich
Bentson, Herdis 2 14 UC Berkeley
Bolin, Rolf 2 15 Hopkins Marine Station
Blackwelder, Eliot 1 8 Dean of Geology Department.
Blackwelder, Eliot 2 15 Dean of Geology Department.
Bryant, Donald L. 2 15 University of Arizona
Coe, Wesley 3 2 Scripps Institute of Oceanography
Drake, Robert 3 5 University of British Columbia
Durham, J. Wyatt 3 5 UC Berkeley
Jahns, Richard H. 1 14 Dean of Earth Sciences
Jahns, Richard H. 3 7 Dean of Earth Sciences
Krauskopf, Konrad, 2 7 Professor of Geology
Marsh, Owen, 3 14 Student, long-time correspondent
Milburn, Patrick 3 9 Former student, touching letter
Remson, Irwin 1 3 Professor of Geology
Tresidder, Donald 3 12 President of Stanford
Weaver, Charles E. 3 13
Wilbur, Ray Lyman 3 15 President of Stanford